<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A comfortable meditation of humane frailtie, and divine mercie in two sermons upon Psalme 146.4. and Psalme. 51.17. The one chiefly occasioned by the death of Katharine, youngest daughter of Mr. Thomas Harlakenden of Earles-Cone in Essex.</title>
            <author>Williamson, Thomas, 1593-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25738</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106233</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841953</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841953</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6574</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15471)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6574)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1337:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A comfortable meditation of humane frailtie, and divine mercie in two sermons upon Psalme 146.4. and Psalme. 51.17. The one chiefly occasioned by the death of Katharine, youngest daughter of Mr. Thomas Harlakenden of Earles-Cone in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Williamson, Thomas, 1593-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Haviland for Iames Boler, dvvelling at the signe of the Marigold in Pauls church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Thomas Williamson.</note>
                  <note>Errata on page 39.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through; some leaves stained and cropped at head.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6574:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6574:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Comfortable MEDITATION OF Humane Frailtie, AND Divine Mercie: IN TWO SERMONS upon PSALME 146.4. AND PSALME 51.17. The one chiefly occaſioned by the death of <hi>Katharine,</hi> youngeſt Daughter of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Harlakenden</hi> of Earles-Cone in Eſſex.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Theſſ. 5.9,10,11,12.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>God hath not appointed us to wrath, but to obtaine ſalvation by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who died for us; that whether we wake or ſleepe, wee ſhould live together with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore comfort your ſelves together, and edifie one another, even as yee alſo doe.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Haviland</hi> for <hi>Iames Boler,</hi> dwelling at the ſigne of the Marigold in PAVLS Church-yard. 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:6574:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>SIC te, ſic ſolare tuas; ſic Iuſta bentae</l>
            <l>Solve tuae, nullo diſſoluenda die.</l>
            <l>Nec me cognatae, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaliſque laboris,</l>
            <l>Nec natae poterit poenituiſſe patrem.</l>
            <l>Ipſe oculos madidus, nobis detergis ocellos,</l>
            <l>Conſortemque <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enes, quâ potesuſque tuam.</l>
            <l>Non ſatis eſt viva prolis quod imagine vivit</l>
            <l>Phoenix Materno quae velut orta rogo eſt;</l>
            <l>Ipſam ſed ſupereſſe velis, dum plectra Davidis</l>
            <l>Tang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, Threicia plus va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ra lyrâ.</l>
            <l>Iam Mauſolaei ſuperaſti dona ſepulchri,</l>
            <l>Hoc ſaxa officium vincit, &amp; aera tuam.</l>
            <l>Non aurum, nec ebur; ſed qua Sacraria condis</l>
            <l>Sacra eſt materies, nobiliorque tibi.</l>
            <l>Nempè dècet caſtam caſta requieſcere iniurna,</l>
            <l>Et quem viva locum ſemper amavit, habet</l>
            <l>Scripturis tumulata ſacris, ubi conditur urna</l>
            <l>Carmen, &amp; artifices exſuperante manus.</l>
            <l>Sigeneris, formaevè canam, morumvè decorem,</l>
            <l>Vile, ait, hoc Sanctus mun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> honor.</l>
            <l>Singula deliban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> plenum mutilabit acervum,</l>
            <l>Hujus &amp; enumerans plurima, parous erit:</l>
            <l>Innumeras meliùs dictura ſilentia laudes.</l>
            <l>Sed tu perge viam, fide marite, ſacram.</l>
            <l>Et ſi quae facimus ſanctiſſima ſentiat umbra,</l>
            <l>Non aliter vellet te meminiſſe ſui.</l>
            <l>Mors indignatur, dehinc fruſtra &amp; fata minantur,</l>
            <l>Dum parat, amiſſam qui dolet, ipſe mori,</l>
            <l>Vivere te ſuadente mori eſt: Dum <hi>Spiritus exit</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itâ ego ſperarim liberiore frui.</l>
            <l>Non ego lectorem moror ultrâ, maxima cujus</l>
            <l>Ingenii pars eſt officioſus amor.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6574:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVL M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. THOMAS HARLAKENDEN, his loving Father.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which in ſome part you have heard, I now make a viſible word, firſt to quicken a little the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of that good ſoule now with God, to whom you had the relation and love of a father: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to doe you the office of comfort and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude amidſt our great loſſe, and indeed, according to the equitie of Gods owne Law, none ſhould make an Epitaphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Monument to that name rather than my ſelfe, becauſe none on earth is ſo nigh of kin. And, ô that I might ſay, what ſhee, though in Paradiſe, yet doth; even as the faith of righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> he being dead, yet ſpeaketh: O that I might raiſe out that exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and copie of goodneſſe, out of yours and mine, and much other private knowledge: For the kingdome of Heaven, the grace of Chriſt in her, it was <hi>Theſaurus in agro abſconditus,</hi> A trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, a pearle of price, private, and hidden in a field of humble innocencie: <hi>Simon</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Onias,</hi> was (as ſaith the ſonne of <hi>Syrach</hi>) both a faire Olive, and a tall Cypreſſe tree: but ſhee was no haughtie Cypreſſe (the more barren, the more high) an Olive, if you will, of love and humble growth, or a fruitfull Vine of low ſtature, as ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Ezech. 17.6.</hi> Yet the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, the honour of her vertues, it ſhall follow, yea though ſhe did not affect it, but ſeemed to flie from it rather, from appearances into the heart: God will have her honoured, he complaines by his Prophet, that the righteous ſhould bee taken away without this
<pb facs="tcp:6574:3"/> good teſtimony, or with a non-conſidering. <hi>Clavus fixus in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co fideli,</hi> (as the Prophet ſpeakes,) A naile faſtened ſo ſure; her bleſſedneſſe can no whit be improved, or impaired, by what wee report. Yet let her light ſhine, even for the glorie of the grace of God, ſuch a goodneſſe ſhould not lye in the grave of our private meditation. <hi>Iehojakim</hi> and his like let them goe; God would have them puniſhed with rottenneſſe in their memorie, that they ſhall not have a man to ſay ſo much, as Ah my brother, ah Lord, or ah his glorie: But this his ſervant the Lord provides her of an everlaſting remembrance, and all that knew her beſt, are knowne to mourne moſt for ſuch a bud, a flower not much paſt the ſpring ſo fallen. Shee fell in her prime, I am ſure not unpitied, not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſhed for. <hi>Artemiſia</hi> Queene of Caria, ſo dearly did ſhee rue the death of <hi>Mauſolus</hi> her husband, that by eating his heart in powder, ſhe thought even to incorporate it to hers, and after ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him the <hi>Mauſolaeum,</hi> that worlds wonder: and faine I would, as you ſee, ſome little pillar to perpetuate and keepe up a while in the world that grace we are now ſpeaking of: but what is mine endevour at the beſt, more than a vapour that appeares for a little time; and then vaniſheth quite away. So you have the firſt reaſon why theſe weake notes dare come into publike light.</p>
            <p>The other is a dutie to the root of that branch: And firſt, of conſolation. It pleaſing the Almightie to reſume that gift hee newly had beſtowed by your hands, this cauſed me, as much as ever did any thing, to looke about mee, even as farre as to mine owne grave; for, <hi>Si hoc in viridi, quid in arido?</hi> and the iſſue of ſome thoughts that may come now to your review. The ſumme is, that we ſet our good, our loſſe, and her advantage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. A Chriſtian at death parts but with a bodie, and that to a fall reſt, for it is totally inſenſible, and perceives neither priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor preſence of good or evill: And they that are long and much exerciſed in this life, know what a good it is to bee quit of evill: Why died not I in the birth, for ſo, ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> ſhould I now
<pb facs="tcp:6574:3"/> be at reſt with the Kings and Counſellors of the earth, and why is life given to the bitter in ſoule, who long and dig for death more than for hid treaſures, and rejoyce exceedingly, and are glad when they finde the grave? <hi>Iob 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, the bodie of a good ſoule reſts in full hope for the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Holy Spirit, the inſtrument of his graces and vertues, yea, the member of Ieſus Chriſt: reaſon, if it hath any light of God in it, would ſhew that ſuch a thing muſt not ſee finall corruption, that have a better reſurrection. See you, I pray, the ſtorie of the dying mother with her ſeven ſons, <hi>2 Macchab. 7.</hi> But bodily diſſolution is painfull, and what can a moment of time bring? Yea, many ſuffer not by once dying, what others doe with patience in a living death of the Collick, Gout, Scyatica, and the like: and through age and conſumptions, dying is oft times with paine in a manner impenceptible, in which caſe ſure the Lord dealt mildly with this his owne ſervant, my yoke fellow, he tempered her ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering according to her feeble abilitie: but the paine, what ere it is, by Gods owne appointment, is the only way and paſſage to end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe joy and bliſſe: And wiſe Heathen, out of a meere pang of morall magnanimitie, have taken it up with comfort: A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian then ſhould heare it, aſsiſted with ſuch a promiſe, and grace; and ſpirit, even with God himſelfe. Thus for what concernes the body, a Chriſtians death you ſee it ſhould not be our diſcomfort.</p>
            <p>And moſt of him, his ſoule it in bleſſefull being after death, and the dead live, that wee need not doubt to talke of our deceaſed friends, as alive, my ſiſter, my brother, my wife, for they live, though not with us, yet much better: Wherefore it were a wrong to them, even our diſcomfortable vaine wiſh, that would have them backe from God, which they by no meanes can deſire; yea, we ſhould wrong our God and Saviour, ſo to undervalue the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate communion with him in glorie for a vile world: And we ſhould wrong our ſelves, not to make Gods will ours, and not to yeeld our paſsive obedience in ſome good meaſure, when the
<pb facs="tcp:6574:4"/> event eſpecially hath revealed his will to us: for beſides the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vaine our daily prayer, <hi>Our Father, Thy will bee done,</hi> we ſtrive againſt the unavoidable will of God, as if a man ſhould thinke much, becauſe hee cannot with his toe overturne the globe of the earth: And what reaſon have we to looke for ſuch a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege, which is not incident to our nature, as the caſe now is? a non ſubjection to death, can any one of all thoſe millions which come betwixt <hi>Adam</hi> and doomeſ-day ſay he had it? Beſides, what thouſands, as we ſee, doth a plague, or a ſiege, or a ſet battell de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure together, that walls and bridges have beene made of the dead carcaſſes, and a poore mercenarie Souldier ſo rightly eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates this common debt of our nature, even to venture upon it hourely for a ſmall pay, eſpecially if hee hath a forward Leader: <hi>Malus mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es qui Imperatorem gemens ſequitur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper.</hi> And wee that have Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe our Guide and Captaine, and the Patriarchs, Prophets, and Apoſtles, with all our holy Anceſtors, our fore runners, ſhould we repine and thinke ſo verie hardly, and be ſo verie heartleſſe for death? <hi>Honorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum eſt ex illo calice bibere quem Imperator noſter deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bavit,</hi> It is our honour, our comfort, to be admitted to the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and communion of the Lords cup; yea, Chriſt hath taken downe the bitterneſſe of the cup of death, and hath left us but the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Col. 1.</hi> That which is behinde; ſome relique of his affliction, as it were a drop to the Ocean: for Chriſt hath not foretaſted only, but ſanctified and ſweetned this cup for us, becauſe by the vertue and merit of his death, hee hath ſeparated hell from us, that the death of Chriſt is the death of death, we can be no worſe by death, if we be in Chriſt, than that from a ſinfull and fraile life, we enter into poſſeſsion of an eſtate or life happie and good above all the heart of man can conceive, an exceedingly exceeding eternall weight of glorie, as the Apoſtle ſpeakes. Hence S. <hi>Auſten</hi> checks himſelfe; What cauſe have I to mourne for a mother, of whoſe happineſſe I may be ſo well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red?
<pb facs="tcp:6574:4"/> And I would not have you to be ignorant concerning them which are aſleepe, ſaith the Apoſtle, that yee ſorrow not even as others which have no hope, 1. Theſſ. 4. It is our ignorance, it is a ſcandall, which Chriſtians give to Infidels, and to the ungodly, not to be ſomewhat comfortable in death: <hi>Chriſtiani genus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum morti expeditum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tacitus,</hi> according to the old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Chriſtian is as a man undaunted in death through faith of a better life: And we, if wee had the faithfull comprehenſion of the bleſſed promiſes we might have, it would make us to take up our croſſe with joy: <hi>Gaudeo deais quae patior,</hi> I rejoyce in my ſufferings, <hi>Col. 1.24.</hi> You ſee the way, that we may be ſtedfaſt in our faith, even to ground our hearts on Chriſt through the word and ſpirit: the exceſſe of our feare ariſeth from the defect of our faith. And now to bring your conſolation home, or a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle neere. Now your childe hath her propertie, her part in Chriſt and all his benefits: You ſee my confidence, did the Lord ever faile to build on the ground ſhe hath laid, true Chriſtian humilitie? God gives grace unto the humble, the grace of remiſsion, and the grace of regeneration, and the grace of perſeverance in both, ſo that in Grace, humilitie in the firſt, ſecond, and third, as S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten</hi> ſayes truly: And could a ſoule bee more truly lowly and meeke, than that we now commemorate. The Lord had moulded her of an ingenuous, innocent, and tender frame, both of minde and body, even for himſelfe, and before the Lambe of God in her white ſtole of ſpotleſſe innocencie and joy, ſhe now is and ſhall bee for evermore, amidſt the ſpirits of the juſt, who in part are come to their perfection, ſo it might ſuffice to our comfort, to have ſaid ſhe was humble. Yet I will tell you of that you know her righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, even and juſt diſpoſicion. And her religion, Lord thou knoweſt it, and I know it, and cannot forget it, how conſtant in the ſtudy of Scriptures? Thoſe of devotion, eſpecially the Pſalmes of <hi>David:</hi> and how continuall in the ſacrifice of her prayers, thou didſt ſmell therein a ſavour of reſt: yea Lord, thou knoweſt ſhee
<pb facs="tcp:6574:5"/> was a pious Monitor, have we not heard this of her, alas we have not prayed together to day: And becauſe a renued preparing, a ſpeciall ſtirring up of the graces that be in us, is required to that maine part of a Chriſtian to dye well and comfortably, I might much aſſure you in this too: So had her native and accidentall weakneſſe inured and minded her long before of the perill ſhe was to paſſe, not without an expectance of death in it: And to that purpoſe the tracts of holy devotion and preparation, they were the moſt of her ſtudy and meditation: The concluſion is, ſo hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, innocent an heart and life, of which you had the experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall knowledge, it muſt be, it is crowned with an happie death.</p>
            <p>Thus I have ſaid enough for your comfort, if not too much for me, and better might have beſeemed another pen or tongue, as ſome may cenſure; but let them thinke as they will, it is no love of errour, yea, the dutie of remembrance, it was due to the Lords ſervant now at reſt and in peace: and the office of conſolation, not like to be done by another, was due to you that remaine on earth.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, I would have extant a teſtimony of my gratitude to you, of whoſe integritie, and love, and godly humilitie, I have had good experience. And though God hath pleaſed to make a breach upon the bond which cauſed the union and relation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene us, and great diſtance of place and dwelling, may threaten to divide, and cut me off from you, yet I muſt reckon you ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst my beſt friends. And by the name wee have now treated of, and what ere was deare in it, I pray you let me be one of yours ſtill: Yea, let this writing lye by you, to informe you thus much, that it proceeds from a minde deeply affected to you and yours. And the Lord Ieſus Chriſt bleſſe you all eternally.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Beckingham</hi> in <hi>Lincoln.</hi> 
                  <date>Iune 16. 1630.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your verie loving Sonne, <hi>Thomas Williamſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:6574:5"/>
            <head>A FVNERAL SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSAL. 146.4.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>His breath goeth forth, he returneth to his earth, in that very day his thoughts periſh.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Pſalme, and the reſt to the end, are much-what of one kinde, both for manner and matter, and ſomething may be ſaid not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſefully from both. Their method or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a circular praying the Lord; like the heavens they move in a circle, and have recourſe to the ſame point; at <hi>Hallelujah</hi> is the beginning, and at <hi>Hallelujah</hi> is the ending.</p>
            <p>And this may be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a circular doctrine or inſtruction, that after this manner wee looke up to God in all our deſignes, not as firſt diſpoſer or mover onely, but as founder and finiſher, <hi>α</hi> and <hi>ω,</hi> firſt efficient, and ſupreme end, to whom all our ſtrength and ſervice refers and bowes, like the ſheaves of <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſonnes to the ſheafe of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, the matter of theſe five laſt Pſalmes, the whole of them is but <hi>Hallelujah;</hi> praiſe ye the Lord, runneth like the bloud in the veines, quite thorow them.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:6574:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And why may not this inſtruct us too, even wherein is every good mans duty, to praiſe God thorowly, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually? The Lord our God, the keeper of Iſrael, neither ſleepeth, nor ſlumbreth; and his Angels, or Seraphims ceaſe not to ſing, Holy, Holy; and Satan and his Angels are ever in circuit to devoure us, and our indevotion to good is ever ſtealing on us; therefore we ſhould not content our ſelves with good beginnings, like the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume of mercy at the end, and be ſtarke dead in the middle, like the Church of <hi>Sardis;</hi> we ſhould not reſt in this, that we lift up our lips ſometime to the Lord in the morning, or end in the evening in our accuſtomed devotions, unleſſe the heart and matter of our day, our life be well beſtowed: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our modell here, wee ſhould bee enwoven and wrought quite thorow; our maine bent ſhould be a <hi>Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah</hi> to praiſe the Lord with all our might, as <hi>David</hi> did with all Iſrael at the bringing home of the Arke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very ſenſible whenſoever we ceaſe to bee of ſervice to the Lord, as <hi>David</hi> was grieved for the breach in <hi>Vzzah,</hi> and therefore called it <hi>Perez-Vzzah,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13. Now the Pſalme in hand is firſt Euchariſticall, a vow of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall praiſe to the Lord, in the two firſt verſes. Secondly, Paraineticall; it exhorts to it upon maine reaſon in the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of the Pſalme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Praiſe yee the Lord. Praiſe the Lord O my ſoule: While I live I will praiſe the Lord; while I have any being;</hi> that is, O my minde or underſtanding meditate thou on God, know him ô my will or inmoſt affection, my very heart-root bee thou ſet for God, yea, and that not for a mood or humour onely, <hi>ſed quum adhuc ego ſum;</hi> while I live, while I have any being, I ſhall praiſe the Lord thorow all times, places, and occaſions.</p>
            <p>Here is the man after God his owne make; So let us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken our ſelves, <hi>ſo ſpeake, and ſo doe, Iames</hi> the ſecond. Eſpecially we who ſucceed the Pſalmiſt in office, ſo ſhould we foretaſte, &amp; pre-digeſt the heavenly gift, and the powers of the world to come, and ſpeake of our God out of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6574:6"/> or out of a ſenſe of that peace and grace which wee preach; and this is <hi>Clarigatio,</hi> as the Roman heralds uſe to ſpeake, an <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> a denouncing warre againſt hell and ſinne, with a ſhrill and piercing ſound.</p>
            <p>Againe, the Pſalme is exhortative, preſſed with good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. The ſumme is this; Sticke cloſe to the Lord by faith and love, for fruitleſſe and vaine is all other confidence in compariſon; in God there is much good-will and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in God there is infinite abilitie and power, in God there is eternall being, hee rules for ever, as wee ſee from the fifth verſe to the end. But humane ſuccour that muſt faile us needs, ſometime in will, ſometime in power, ever in dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as in the third and fourth verſes, <hi>Put not your truſt in Princes, nor in the ſonne of man in whom there is no helpe: His breath goeth forth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed, Chriſt is the Prince of peace, happy are we that have him our hope, for as he is the ſonne of man, the branch of <hi>David;</hi> ſo he is <hi>germen Iehovae, the ſeed of Iehovah, Eſa.</hi> 4.2. <hi>The Lord our righteouſneſſe, Ierem.</hi> 23.5. <hi>Ex homine, non per hominem,</hi> borne of a woman, but by the Holy Ghoſt, and the fullneſſe of the Godhead dwelleth in him perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the helpe of Chriſt, is the helpe of God.</p>
            <p>But meere ſons of men; every ſecond cauſe whatſoever is no ſalvation, no ſolid helpe, no merit or efficacy to build upon. The grace of a Prince is a ſhade under which all fleſh is glad to feed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. and <hi>Seneca</hi> wondereth how <hi>Polybius</hi> could weepe, <hi>Propitio Caeſare,</hi> being in grace with <hi>Caeſar:</hi> yet <hi>put not your truſt in Princes,</hi> not in the ingenious (as the word ſignifieth) or magnificent? No: Then the Pſalmiſt takes off our truſt from all the world, and there is not that thing in it which is to be truſted and celebrated for ever, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nothing in the world is for ever, and God his Deputies in office, are <hi>filii hominis,</hi> in eſſence like other men: and ſo the beſt humane confidence is but <hi>pons ſublicius,</hi> a woodden bridge, very ready to ſinke under us; yea, <hi>ſcipio arundincus,</hi> as he ſaid of the King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> a broken reed, perillous to be truſted on, when the waves of death, and judgement, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6574:7"/> ſpirituall diſtreſſes ariſe and ſwell; and therefore <hi>Hallelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah,</hi> praiſe God, and doe not deifie or propoſe to your hearts a reſt in the creature, for it is all mutable.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>His breath goeth forth, he returneth to the earth, in that very day his thoughts periſh.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Here a treble note of humane imbecillity: Firſt, from that which is the forme or the fountaine of lively being; <hi>Spiritus exit, His ſpirit,</hi> or <hi>his breath goeth forth:</hi> Secondly, from the matter that he is made of; <hi>Et revertetur in terram ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>am, and he ſhall returne into his earth:</hi> Thirdly, from the effects that he purpoſeth or produceth; <hi>In illo die pertbunt omnes cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones corum, in that very day his thoughts periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word <hi>ſpirit</hi> is ſometime taken ſubſtantially for the ſoule, <hi>Lord Ieſus receive my ſpirit, Acts</hi> 7. <hi>And the ſpirit returneth to God that gave it, Eccleſ.</hi> 12. So Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> and others take this place, his ſoule goeth forth accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that, as her ſoule was going forth or departing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.18.</p>
            <p>Againe, it is uſed effectually for breath or reſpiration; <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſpiritum, Take away their breath, and they die, Pſal.</hi> 104.29. <hi>And the body without the ſpirit is dead,</hi> that is, without breath, <hi>Iames</hi> 2. For compare breath to a maſſie body, and ſuch is the rarity of it, or thinneſſe, that it ſeemes to bee a ſpirit or ſpirituall; and conſider it with the ſoule, and ſuch is the uſe of it, that it ſeemes no leſſe to informe the body, than the ſpirit it ſelfe, by which it is. But the argument is good however the word be taken: ſay our very eſſence, and forme, and ſoule is fleeting as a Pilgrim, and ready to paſſe from its Inne, to goe forth of the body, therefore <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> faſten mainly upon Jehovah, becauſe man is very ſoone out of being, ſo ſoone done, his ſoule goeth forth. Againe, what a brittleneſſe is this? if we ſay a breath, an aiery ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſo thinne and vaniſhing it is, that it is ſcarce viſible, if we ſay a breath, it is a tye which combines ſoule and body, and props up even Princes from mouldring into aſhes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Heavens and the Elements, God made man for his glory, a creature able to conceive him, and to ſpeake and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6574:7"/> his excellencie, and by thoſe two rich donatives, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, underſtanding and ſpeech; the Lord put man in a ſtate of perfection, denied to all other creatures below, namely, to be admitted into the immediate preſence of God, and moſt eſpecially to behold and publiſh his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſo a ſoule underſtanding and reaſonable; <hi>animus aeterna mente delibatus,</hi> (as the Oratour ſpeaketh) a ſpirit breathed into man by the immediate act of God himſelfe; it is ſuch a dowry wherein man is farre nobler and better than the very heavens, and therefore man had need of ſomewhat to abate the riſing thoughts of the ſoule, and the Lord hath given us therefore <hi>Stimulum in carne,</hi> a mortality in the body to buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet us;
<q>
                  <hi>His breath goeth forth.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, there is the deaths head, the mortality of man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that a very breath is as much as his being is worth: Our ſoule that <hi>ſpiraculum vitarum,</hi> the Lord inſpired it, not into <hi>Adams</hi> eye or eare, or mouth, but into his noſtrills, which may ſhew to man his imbecillity, <hi>Cujus anima in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus,</hi> whoſe ſoule is in his noſtrills, and dependeth upon a breath as it were, for the very ſoule muſt away, if but breath expires, ſoule and breath goe forth both together.</p>
            <p>Now heare yee this, all ye People, ponder it high and low, your Caſtle is built upon a verie aire, the ſubſiſtence is <hi>in flatu narium,</hi> in a blaſt, that is out in the twinckling of an eye; Wherefore <hi>David</hi> maketh a queſtion, ſaying, <hi>Domine, quid eſt homo? Lord, what is man?</hi> Hee anſwereth himſelfe alſo; <hi>Man is a vaniſhing ſhadow, Pſal.</hi> 144. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, A ſhadow of ſmoake, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the dreame of a ſhadow ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as the Poet ſpeaketh.) And bleſſed therefore are the poore in ſpirit, this advantage have all afflicted ones, that they have checks enough to call them home, to make them ſee they be but men: The curtaine of honour, profit, or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, hard it is and rare to draw that aſide, when it is ſpread over us, man in honour underſtandeth not, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. To great ones therefore be it ſpoken, the Pſalme intendeth it to verie Princes, <hi>His br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>th goeth forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:6574:8"/>
            <p>And breathleſſe man, who before amazed the bruit crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the majeſtie of his eye, no better is hee to the eye now, than the duſt and gravell, and chill clay under our ſhooe:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>—Iacet ingens littore truncus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Avulſumque humeris caput, &amp; ſine nomine corpus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The Poet ſpeakes of King <hi>Priam.</hi> Now ceaſe from the man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, <hi>Iſay</hi> 2. Ten thouſand graves, and wormes, and paſſing-bels, cannot give us a truer touch. <hi>Waldus,</hi> a rich Merchant of <hi>Lyons,</hi> ſeeing a man on the ſudden breathe his laſt in the ſtreets: So was hee taken with it, that as ſuddenly he turned his old courſe, fell to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the Scriptures, and became in earneſt a Preacher, and Founder of the Chriſtians called <hi>Waldenſes:</hi> Yee ſee what a point this is, and of what uſe, his breath goeth forth. Our Saviour hid himſelfe from the unſought honours of the Jewes: and ſo ſhould we, had we learned but this, we would withdraw ſure from the perillous dignities and delights of the times. But as <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> the ſame morning hee went out to ſue for the Prieſthood, ſaluting his mother ſaid, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum niſi Pontificem ſe non reverſurum,</hi> That he would never come home but high Prieſt: So (my brethren in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie) doe not ſome of us in purſuit of honour, take leave of our charge, which ſhould be as our mother deare unto us; but we goe out, as reſolved not to come to reſidence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an high Prieſthood; for we never thinke on it, that our ſpirit hath but this to ſhew for its reſidence in the world, a breath, and if the Lord daſh that, we die, if he take away his finger, we fall away like water: Now therefore, that we may all grow to more ſinceritie, let us, I pray you, accuſtome our eares and eyes to man dying, it would certainly looſen us much from this world, to ſee, and to feele, and to handle this truth, as it were, his ſpirit, his breath goeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orth. And this for the ſubſtance of the act, the going forth of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, yee ſee what it meaneth.</p>
            <p>See we now the continuedneſſe, <hi>Exit, it goeth;</hi> as if it were now preſently in its paſſe to ſhew this, that <hi>Homo vivens
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6574:8"/> contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> è moritur,</hi> That by the verie act of living wee are dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that life is a continued death, our candle lightens, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes and dies: as in the paſſing of an houre-glaſſe, everie minute ſome ſand falleth, and the glaſſe once turned, no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can intreat the ſands to ſtay, till they are drawen out: So is our life, it ſhortens and dies everie minute, and we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not beg a minute of time backe, and that we call death, is but the terme of it, or conſummation; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ita ultimo die fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, omni perit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca:</hi> Many be our partiall or pettie deaths, ſorrow, ſickneſſe, miſhap, but death is incloſed in the bowels of our life, and is eſſentiall with it. <hi>Spiritus exit: His ſpirit goeth forth. Lycurgus</hi> ſaid, that according to the threefold age of man, a threefold ſalutation might bee uſed, you are welcome, or you come in a good houre; God keepe you, or ſtand in a good houre; God ſpeed you, or goe in a good houre: to ſhew that from the age of fiftie and forward, we are taking our leave, our ſpirit is going forth, but ſo fraile and fluid is life, that at all ages &amp; times we may be bid, God ſpeed, we may have our <hi>Vale,</hi> or goe in a good houre. For once imbarqued, we are going to the Port. The going out of the Cradle is the entring into the grave, to have a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and to be borne, is to breed or be in travell, yea to bee darted, or put in a ſlight to an end; Therefore <hi>Thales</hi> was wont to ſay, that there is no difference betweene life and death, and being thereupon demanded, <hi>Tu ergo quid non moreris?</hi> Why doeſt not thou dye then? Becauſe, ſaith he, there is no difference: So that if we ſeeke the act of living, our hearts, if we be wiſe, ſhould be eſtabliſhed againſt dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe life and death are eſſentiall to one another, or include one another, and it is as naturall to dye, as to live, and in themſelves therefore to be regarded both alike: <hi>Quid ergo novi, ſi mortalis natus moriatur?</hi> Let it not bee ſtrange to us, that we ſhould die, being borne dying or mortall. <hi>His ſpirit goeth forth: Exit.</hi> And to us that bee Miniſters in the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt, let this word bee to us a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, like <hi>Bezaleel</hi> and <hi>Aholibah,</hi> by the grace that is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us, we are maſter-builders, but of the Lords Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6574:9"/> or Church militant on the earth, and wee are gentle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, ſaith the Apoſtle, even as a Nurſe cheriſheth her children, affectionately deſirous of you, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3. even ſo with piteous heart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> looke wee upon our charge, for they be earthly tabernacles, dying men and women: their ſoule and ſpirit ſtand upon their lips as it were: <hi>It goeth forth; Spiritus exit.</hi> O let us tender them therefore, and apply our preſent ſpeedy releefe, leſt they fall out of our hands, before we have diſpenced them the bread of life, of which Chriſt hath made us overſeers and ſtewards, and as upon the bed of our languiſhing, we would not have a loftie or profound, but a gracious word come to us; ſo ſeeing wee deale with ſuch, whoſe living is a continued dying, let us ſeeke that our divinitie may be as profitable as may be to ſave: <hi>Salus populi ſuprema lex eſto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I come to the libertie of the ſpirit, that it recedes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violate; 1. In Act, <hi>it goeth:</hi> 2. In eſſence, <hi>it goeth forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our ſpirit is free in the Act, it is not haled, not ſnatched out, as it were, <hi>it goeth forth.</hi> A ſoule in life ſealed to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie by the firſt fruits of the ſpirit hath its good iſſue, its free paſſing, its hopes even in death: for let this breath fade, <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis Deus,</hi> God who cannot lye, becauſe he hath ſaid it, be we ſure he will ſtand nigh us in that exigencie, and begin to helpe where man leaveth, <hi>not ſuffering his to be tempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove that they are able,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. The holy Spirit, whoſe name is the Comforter, will not omit and leave off his owne act or office in the great needs of death. Hence good <hi>Hilarion</hi> having ſerved the Lord Chriſt ſeventie yeares, checkes his ſoule that it was ſo loth at the laſt to part, to goe forth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Egredere, ô anima mea, egredere;</hi> Goe forth, my ſoule, goe forth: And devout <hi>Simeon</hi> ſueth for a manumiſſion, <hi>Lord, now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace, according to thy word:</hi> And this is the freedome of the act, the Spirit goeth forth; it yeelds, yea it goes and paſſes freely, that is, it taketh up, or embraceth the Croſſe of Chriſt, as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth us to doe. But is the act at our will and libertie? not ſimply, we may not <hi>projicore animam,</hi> thruſt or caſt forth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6574:9"/> our breath or ſpirit, <hi>Spiritus Exit,</hi> it goeth forth, ſtrive wee muſt to caſt the world out of us, we may not caſt our ſelves out of the world. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> dareth not diſſolve himſelfe, though he could wiſh to be diſſolved, God muſt part that which he joynes, God giveth, and God taketh away; and if God ſay as he doth to <hi>Lazarus, Exi foras,</hi> come forth, with faithfull <hi>Steven</hi> we muſt reſigne our Spirit, and all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hands. When God biddeth us yoke, he is the wiſeſt man that yeeldeth his necke moſt willingly; when our grand Captaine recalls us, we muſt take the retreit in good part, but it is heatheniſh to force out the ſoule, for when the miſdeeming fleſh amidſt our diſaſters, will not liſten with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience for God his call, but rather ſhake off the thought of divine providence quite, then are wee ready to curſe God and die, and that is probably, to leape <hi>e fumo in ſtammam,</hi> out of the ſinne of ſelfe-murder into hell; no, but God will have our ſpirits to paſſe forth upon good termes. <hi>Spiritus exit,</hi> the ſpirit goeth forth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſpirit goeth free or inviolate in eſſence, death is not the end, but the out-going of the ſoule, a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migration or journey from one place to another. It goeth forth, ſo the character of our weakneſſe we ſee in the iſſue, it is an argument of our eternity, for man indeed is periſhing, but ſo is not his ſpirit, <hi>Non ſimul perit anima, &amp; animal.</hi> The Phaenix goes forth, or out of his aſhes, <hi>the ſpirit returneth to God that gave it, Eccleſ.</hi> 12. that is, it abides ſtill, and as in the body it pleaſed God to incloſe the ſoule for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo it may as well exiſt elſewhere without it, if God will, for it hath no riſe at all from the clay, yea, it beares in it immortality, an image of that breſt whence it is breathed. The ſeparate and very abſtract acts of the ſpirit, even while it is in the body, the wondrous viſions of the Lord to his Prophets, uſually when their bodies were bound up in ſleepe; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> his rapture when he knew not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was in the bodie or out of it: the admirable inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and arts of men manifeſt the ſoules-ſelfe-conſiſting. Not <hi>Socrates,</hi> and <hi>Cato,</hi> and the civilized heathen onely, but the very ſavage beleeve this, and ſo entertaine death, <hi>Vt exitum,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6574:10"/> non ut exitium,</hi> as a diſſolution, not as a deſtruction, <hi>Spiritus exit, his ſpirit goeth forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we know ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. we are ſure God the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt, doth no create, redeeme, and regenerate man for the meere uſe of a wretched ſhort life; and who can imagine, ſo monſtrouſly, that of all men the good and righteous, and of all creatures man, for whom the reſt are made, and who hath the uſe or ſoveraignty of all, yet by farre that he ſhould be the moſt vile and miſerable of all? but ſure it were ſo, if in this life onely we had hope, ſeeing there be no lower creatures that are capable of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and terrours of conſcience, and feares of death, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of future judgement, yea, not ſo ſubject to bodily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe. But account mee not dead ſaid the holy martyr, for I ſhall certainely live and never die. And the martyrs, ſo vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous (as we ſee) amidſt the ruines and deſtructions of the body, had ſomething in them ſurely more than duſt: A Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, <hi>Hermes Triſmegiſtus,</hi> dying, ſaid; <hi>Mourne not for me as if I were dead, for I returne to the happieſt City.</hi> Above all Jeſus Chriſt giveth us an expreſſe watch-word, <hi>Nothing is able to kill the ſoule, Mat.</hi> 10. And <hi>Martin Luther</hi> going to give up his account before the Emperour, received this Eccho from the people, feare not them that cannot kill the ſoule. <hi>Mundus minetur, aeſtuet,</hi> Death by all its pyoning takes but a fort of clay; <hi>Animus ad ſedes ſuas &amp; cognata ſydera recurrit,</hi> the ſpirit as new hatched goeth forth to live ſtill, like as the light iſſuing from the Sunne, dieth not at Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing, but goeth ſome whither elſe with the Sunne; ſo life that iſſues from the ſoule, goes with its owne principle, and abides with it; ſo Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the divine, to be better enabled to his baniſhment, he had a viſion of this by ſpeciall privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, a ſight of the immortall ſafe ſubſiſtence of the ſoule af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death, under the altar the cuſtody of Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9 And thence is Saint <hi>Pauls, Ne contriſtemini,</hi> ſorrow not as hopeleſſe men, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. Yea, bee we nured to a certaine faith, and frequent thought of this, and a fairer flower the booke of God yeeldeth not, than the immortality of Saints in bliſſe. Hence the great patience of the Saints, hence the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6574:10"/> challenge of death, <hi>Vbi mors victoria,</hi> O death thou wilt take away our breath; Alas how ſmall a loſſe, ſeeing no death can divide us from Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38. and <hi>ſpiritus exit,</hi> ſeeing the ſpirit doth but <hi>migrare,</hi> it goeth untouched in eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and inviolate.</p>
            <p>The maine iſſue of this firſt point is, that ſeeing our breath, our ſpirit goeth forth, that wee make ſure proviſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of ſome harbour or ſanctuary, that we get us into the Arke before the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ud, that we gather our Manna, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to our eternall Sabbath now in the Even of this life, <hi>Qui laborat in veſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re Sabbati, veſce ur in Sabbato,</hi> ſay the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, and what an exceeding ſtrength will it be to us when we are weake in minde and body, that our ſpirit is to paſſe ſafely and comfortably, that we have a refuge, a <hi>terminus ad quem</hi> for our ſpirit; ſo let us forecaſt for it by a true appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and faith of the loves and promiſes of God in Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>O my Dove that art in the clefts of the rock,</hi> ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.14. The wounds of Chriſt, are the clefts of the rocke, therein let us cove&amp;r hide us over ſoule and body, let us make ſure of a rightfull hold in that rocke of our ſalvation, through faith and repentance, and ſo our ſpirits will grow acquainted with the peace of conſcience, and the joyes of the Holy Ghoſt, and the ſenſe and hopes of the promiſed recompence, and ſo ſhall alſo we be well compoſed and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified for our migration or paſſage, even that our ſpirit go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth of an earthly veſſell, but into an eternall and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed receptacle.</p>
            <p>I come to the ſecond branch of the text: the ſecond note of mans imbecillity from the matter that he is made of: <hi>Et revertetur in terram ſuam, and he returneth to his earth. He returneth:</hi> The body of man before his fall was beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and amiable in the eye of God, and awfull in the eye of the creature, and exacts in its owne temper, and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall by privilege ſealed in the tree of life; but ſince that ſinne came into the world, the body of man incloſeth a death, a ſelfe-ruining, beſide outward violence, and perills of conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, none of which were incident to his pure eſtate; ſo man returnes to his earth without contradiction, hee hath
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6574:11"/> no helpe for it. The ſpirit which holdeth up the elements together in a body, when that goeth forth, each of them fall backe to their owne principles; earth goeth to its earth, according to God his ordinance, <hi>duſt thou art, and to duſt thou ſhalt returne, Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>Nicodemus</hi> thought it ſtrange, but in this ſenſe it is true, we re-enter the bowels of our mother. The ſonne of <hi>Syrach</hi> calleth the earth, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of us all, <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 40. So <hi>Brutus</hi> wiſely tooke the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, when being warned to kiſſe his mother, kiſſed the earth. <hi>His earth.</hi> Earth we ſee goeth, very nigh us, it is our earth, not onely the matter or rocke out of which wee are hewen, but the matter whereof wee conſiſt, our ingredient, and co-eſſentiall with us, that I may ſay with the Prophet <hi>Ieremy, O earth, earth, earth, heare the word of the Lord.</hi> Trim wee never ſo nicely, we are earth, <hi>Lutea progenies,</hi> an off-ſpring of earth, yea, <hi>pulvinaria,</hi> as the Romans ſtiled their Temples, veſſels or beds made up or ſtuft with duſt, and ſhall we dote upon our earth? Shall we ſuffer our immorta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſpirit to goe out like a ſtarveling, and over-care for what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernes the bodie, and over-decke the daughter of ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? know we not that our very make is ſuch, that earth, that the chambers of death ſtand like the houſes of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Tribunes, wide open for us night and day, and very uſually man ſleepeth, and never riſeth againe, and walketh, but never returneth againe, unleſſe it be into his earth.</p>
            <p>The men of Anathoh ſaid to the Prophet <hi>Ieremie, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie not in the name of the Lord, that thou dye not, Ier.</hi> 11. But to you, my fellow-labourers, I ſay, propheſie in the feare of God; for we ſhall die, becauſe we ſhall be diſſolved, and returne to our earth, wee know not how ſoone, and if this doth not quicken, our account being ſo nigh at hand, what will? And of all Gods Officers, we his eſpeciall Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, how ſhall wee turne us on the bed of death, if we have betrayed the immediate worke and buſineſſe of our Soveraigne? The Indian Prieſts or Brachmanes, ſo verie ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate were they from the body, that they are ſaid, <hi>Interrâ eſſe, &amp; non in terrâ eſſe;</hi> To be, and not to bee on the earth: A Miniſter of Chriſt his Goſpell much rather hee ſhould bee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6574:11"/> unglued, and abſtracted from this earth, the body, like a ſtarre already fixed in Heaven: But wee care what wee can for our body, and ſo tender it oft times, that wee forget our God, and yet nevertheleſſe wee ſhall returne to our earth; and when our turne commeth, what a crowne of rejoycing ſhould it be, to thinke that we have waſted in body, by win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſoules, and have truly ſought to turne men to God, though it turne us into the earth, <hi>ſtantem &amp; praedicantem mori?</hi> But beſide counſell, the Lord hath comfort for this point in the iſſue, namely, that thus God ordaineth by his returne into earth, to refine and turne our vile bodies, to bee like the glorious bodie of Jeſus Chriſt: Hee that was wrapt up into the third Heavens, and knew what he ſaith, S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes it, Yea (ſaith hee) as the corne liveth not except it die, and be caſt into the earth, ſo wee are not clarified, not made bleſſed bodies, but by a returne into the earth. So then with an Eagles eye by faith, pierce wee thorow, and looke beyond the grave, and wee ſhall diſcerne and ſee an incomparable light of grace, to which the Lord worketh our returne into earth, our verie diſſolution.</p>
            <p>But if the ſpirit of him that raiſed Jeſus from the dead be in you, he that raiſed Chriſt from the dead, ſhall quicken al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo your mortall bodies, by, or becauſe of the Spirit that dwelleth in you, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. our earth is Chriſts body, know ye not that your bodies are the members of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. Dead and withered as we be, wee are ſtill united to Chriſt, it is not death that can ſeparate us from him, <hi>for I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that neither death nor life,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. and by vertue of this myſticall conjunction with Chriſt, even according to our whole man, doubt we nothing, but our firſt reſurrection by the ſame ſpirit, is an earneſt and certaine pledge of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reſurrection; for that ſame quickening ſpirit of Chriſt, which now dwelleth in us, and uniteth us to him, it is hee that made our bodies out of the earth at firſt, yea, which made the earth it ſelfe, and the whole world out of nothing; and therefore hee can and will, as hee hath witneſſed, fetch our bodies backe from the earth to which they are returned, and that becauſe they are yet the members of Chriſt Jeſus
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6574:12"/> though the ſame ſpirit, and his owne temples God will ſurely reare them up againe, yea, though they lye in the duſt, and the latter temples ſhall have farre more beautie than the former, according to his word.</p>
            <p>I proceed to the third and laſt note of humane weakneſſe from the effects, that which man purpoſeth or produceth: <hi>In illo die peribunt omnes cogitationes eorum, In that verie day his thoughts periſh: The night commeth that no man can worke, Iohn</hi> 9.4. The dead are out of office; ſo it is of our nature, to leave our humane purpoſes crackt and broken in the verie midſt, my dayes are paſt, my enterpriſes are bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, <hi>Iob</hi> 8. In that verie day our life is defined to bee a vapour that appeares a little time, and then vaniſheth, <hi>Iam.</hi> 4. <hi>My dayes are a ſpan long,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, Feciſti dies meos pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marios, Pſal.</hi> 39. and wee are but as yeſterday, <hi>Iob</hi> 8. So though we make a buſtle for a life time in this world, that is all our projects go not on into another world, and life is ſuch a minute, ſuch a drop of the bucket, <hi>Gutta è ſitula,</hi> as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh, that our terrene thoughts periſh all in that ve-day that they were hatched, as it were.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> had not elbow-roome, not ſpace enough in the world for his thoughts. <hi>Xerxes</hi> had ſuch thoughts againſt Greece, that he undertaketh an expedition ſo huge and great, that ſeas and mountaines are even ſpurned out of his way. And <hi>Iulian</hi> madly projects a finall and utter extirpation of all Chriſtendome: Vaſt and high thoughts all, yet a bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, no ſooner up than deaded, daſht that verie day that they were conceived, as it were. The Parable of that certaine rich man, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. ſheweth how verie periſhing is the figure and thought of this world, and it is well ſhadowed at the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Popes, when hee that is new called paſſeth on, the Maſter of the Ceremonies holds up an handfull of flax at the end of a dry reed, and ſetting fire to it, ſaith aloud, <hi>Pater ſancte, ſic tranſit gloria mundi;</hi> Holy Father, ſo paſſes the worlds glorie: <hi>Fortuna vitrea,</hi> It is a glaſſie condition, as that noble Lady, the Lady <hi>Iane Gray</hi> admoniſhed the Lieutenant at her death, now let us not bee too eager on it therefore, but keepe in, and limit our terrene thoughts and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6574:12"/> purpoſes, yea let us trample the Moone, the world under our feet, give it the loweſt place in our affections, as the Lord repreſents it in the twelfth of the <hi>Revelation.</hi> Everie Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man like young <hi>Hannibal, tactis ſacris,</hi> hee voweth no leſſe in baptiſme, <hi>ſe cum primum poſſet hoſtem fore,</hi> even to hate the world in compariſon, and not to ſpend a thought for it, if it lay in his way to God and his grace. But, by thoughts, not only the worldly, but the verie quinteſſence, or moſt excellent effects of the minde of man, are meant; namely, that all which is not above humanitie is moſt peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing. The beſt humane good is the rich furniture of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Arts, and Sciences; and, <hi>Let not the wiſe glorie in his wiſdome,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>Eſay</hi> 9. and, <hi>God knoweth the thoughts of the wiſe are but vaine,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. uneffectuall to ſalvation: ſhould any creature ſwell or preſume on this good? The depths of the Schooles or State, what are they? An anchor pitched in the aire, a wall of breath about us, which if the Lord but puſh at us, are gone <hi>verſo pollice,</hi> with a wet finger (as they ſay) and when the darts of temptation, and the furie of diſeaſe, and the fearefull wan lookes of death and judgement come to us, in that verie day theſe thoughts pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. <hi>O fallacem hominum ſpem! ô inanes noſtras contentiones!</hi> Thus the Oratour laments the death of his learned <hi>Horten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius.</hi> But ô the buckler of faith, the helmet of ſalvation! at other times we may talke, and ſay our wits have made us, at the evill houre nothing but God can eaſe us, no skill can cure us but of God his mercie in Chriſt Jeſus: and <hi>Luther</hi> therfore ſaid well, that men were beſt Chriſtians in death, becauſe when learning, policie, friends, and breath, and all goe from us, if we be wiſe, we then goe from our ſelves, our owne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, and with all our ſtrength and might, reſt and repoſe on God, and his eſpeciall favour and mercie in Chriſt Jeſus revealed in the word; againe, it is a comfort at this verie day, that <hi>In illo die peribunt omnes cogitationes eorum,</hi> the Devill and the world league, and ſet in together, and worke their ſpleene out againſt the Church of Chriſt, and even plow it up before them, fierce and cruell be their thoughts, but they are fraile: the Holy Ghoſt reſembleth them to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6574:13"/> graſſe on the houſe tops, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 129. one would thinke they were good corne by their growing, they are vile graſſe, and ſuch as is without bleſſing. <hi>Iulians</hi> thoughts againſt the Church, were <hi>nubiculae citò tranſiturae,</hi> clouds ſoone over, as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> propheſied, They gave up the ghoſt in one day as it were. The end of the upright God ſets a marke upon it, that it is peace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. but the union of his enemies God will disjoynt it, and they ſhall walke, as wee hope at this day, in <hi>Baal-perizin,</hi> in the valley of diviſion, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14. Counſels againſt God ſhall not ſtand, not laſte, not a day in compariſon, <hi>In that very day his thoughts periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But are the thoughts of men ſo periſhing, it is matter of advice then that we redeeme the ſpanne of time wee have, husband it well, and on good thoughts, and to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, and there be thoughts, as wee ſee in <hi>Maries</hi> choice, which ſhall not periſh with our dayes, and of which no time ſhall bereave us. Bleſſed are they that die in the Lord, they reſt from their labours, and their workes follow them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. The thoughts of Gods worſhip, good workes have their abiding fruit for ever, and when all faile us they follow, goe along with us after death in their reward and crowne, but the bent of our hearts if it be on by matters, we may ſay, what is this we doe? what fruit will this afford us in or after death, <hi>In that very day our thoughts are cut off and periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our dayes are a declining ſhadow, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102. and the ſhadow declines and lengthens, as the Sunne goeth off or on us: when it is direct or meridian ſhort is our ſhadow, and ſtretched out at even, when the light of Chriſt is far from us, then according to the mold of our owne blinde thoughts, our ſhadow lengthens, <hi>for life is our ſhadow, Iob</hi> 14. but then we thinke of death as farre removed, <hi>In hoc enim fallimur quod mortem proſpicimus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca.</hi> Now let our eyes be truly inlightened, and all thoſe thoughts periſh, and we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive life ſliding ſwifter away than a Weavers ſhuttle, <hi>Iob</hi> 7. and ſo the Lord is ſaid to ſhorten our dayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. not that he cuts off, or depriveth us of that time, which hee had determined, but of that which our owne thoughts have min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: And, ô we vaine and blinde, that thinke thus, as if wee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6574:13"/> were at a fee with death, and never to be removed. <hi>Nullius vita non ſpectat in craſtinum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> wee thinke all, to morrow we ſhall live, and we ſhall live better to morrow, and the life we forge and fancie to us, failes us, even before we thinke on it; <hi>In that verie day his thoughts periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be we therefore adviſed to faſten on the preſent time, to repent to day, and beleeve to day, let us provoke our hearts to good purpoſes, and to day let us put our hands to practiſe them. But there be who thinke or dreame, rather of future expiations or ſatisfactions to be made after death, of a releaſe after a time in helliſh durance: but theſe are groundleſſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing thoughts. It is for men once to dye, but after death commeth judgement, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. Therefore the tree of our life, while it hath a ſtanding, let it bend to God-ward, and then we ſhall both ſtand and fall to our owne Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and let us ſeeke preſently to bee reconciled to God, through the pretious purgation of our ſoules, which is through faith in Chriſt his bloud, and then wee ſhall never be confounded, our thoughts ſhall not periſh, or bee made void, <hi>Praeveniendus ergo dies eſt, qui praevenire conſuevit,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſten:</hi> wee muſt trim our lamps betime with the oyle of faith, and love, and prevent the day of death, leſt it prevent us, our eternitie of woe or bliſſe, wee ſhould not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard it to after-thoughts, and to ſecond plots, yea, ſurely it cannot be mended afterward: the watchleſſe virgins, becauſe unprovided then, were undone for ever; and though ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing learnt them wit, they had no time to practiſe it: <hi>In that verie day his thoughts periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to you eſpecially (my Brethren in the Miniſterie) let me ſpeake in the words of S. <hi>Paul; As we have opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie let us die good, Gal.</hi> 6.10. let us be doing good while wee may:—<hi>Dum ſupereſt Lacheſi quod torqueat:</hi>—Should ſuch as wee caſt in our thoughts, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſerve our ſelves or the times for a ſeaſon, and thinke then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſerve the Lord in his Vineyard, perhaps at even, but when our carnall thoughts have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched up to their ends: alas, while wee ſo thinke, while our thoughts are in our hearts, our thoughts may periſh, the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6574:14"/> hand of Juſtice may write bitter things againſt us in that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie moment; high is our race, and life is periſhing, heavenly be our thoughts; let us take that good of our high calling at the firſt opportunitie, the world ſhould ſtoope to it; for the faſhion of the world paſſeth away, but the Crowne is uncorruptible which God reſerveth for us, if wee finiſh our courſe, with a conſcience of his ordinance, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with feare and trembling.</p>
            <p>The Atticke Oratours (ſaith <hi>Quintilian</hi>) are, <hi>Eloquentiae, quadam frugalitate contenti, ac ſemper manum intra pallium continentes;</hi> juſt ſo, many of us doe thinke with <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> we can plead for God in ſober ſilence, husbanding both our profeſſing and preaching of Chriſt Jeſus for feare of the Jewes, leſt we ſhould run into ſuſpition with great ones, and hazard our ſtocke of worldly favours. The argument of my Text is good to raiſe our diligence, namely that we may bee called to dye, in the midſt of our ambitious and terrene thoughts, and ſo to dye before wee have begun to live, and ſo we may live and dye in vaine, and without Uſe: a wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched miſhap eſpecially in a moſt ſpirituall and heavenly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, a Prophet, a Seer of the Lord to periſh before hee hath done any good, a worthleſſe caſe, and moſt to be feared. To conclude, heare we the words of our Savior to his Apoſtles, <hi>What I ſay unto all, I ſay unto you, Watch, Mat.</hi> 26. and heare what <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whatſoever thy hand findeth to doe, doe it, for there is no worke, no device nor wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the grave, whither thou goeſt, Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>In that verie day his thoughts periſh.</hi>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:6574:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A FVNERAL SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSAL. 51.17.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A broken and a contrite heart O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S all civill bodies or common-wealths, ſo that of the Jewes was made up of three diverſe parts: the rich, the middle ſort, the poore; and ſo their oblations were diverſe, from the herd, the flock, the fowles of the aire; and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe often was their end and acceptation: he in the impurity of his heart killeth an oxe, or ſacrificeth a kid, <hi>Decollat canem,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, is as if he cut off a dogs necke, ſo little is the Lord affected to the worſhip wee doe him in meere ceremony; but the honeſt contrite ſoule, the poore in ſpirit, that comes trembling with his paire of turtle doves, repentance and faith, to this man will I looke ſaith the Lord, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 66. The poore ſervice we doe him, if it be in ſpirit, and in truth, he takes delight in it, wherefore <hi>David</hi> here at the 15. verſe, praying for ability to praiſe, or worſhip the Lord aright, ſets it out; Firſt, by negation, even what it is not in compariſon; thou deſireſt not ſacrifice, thou delighteſt not in burnt offerings: Secondly, hee poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively concludes what indeed that is, which indeed God wills, and likes; the ſacrifices of God are the contrite ſpirit, <hi>A broken and a contrite heart O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:6574:15"/>
            <p>Not that the Jewiſh rights were not Gods ordinances, or were then in abrogation, <hi>in ſepultura,</hi> in their buriall; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe outward forms or performances did never ſatisfie not pleaſe the Lord without the ſacrifice and ſervice of the heart, a lip-devotion, a deed done, an heartleſſe manner of worſhip is not that which delights the Lord, or profits us; yea, if there be no heart, no ſoule in it, it is a ſhining ſinne, it is abominable, as if we bleſt an Idoll, as if a Jew had offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſwines bloud, <hi>The ſacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to the Lord, Pro.</hi> 21.27.</p>
            <p>But a cup of cold water, ſaith our Saviour, and the leaſt ſparke of zeale out of a true heart, though mixt with much infirmity, yet goeth not away unregarded; this, when the widow, good ſoule, came in with her mite, the Lord calls his diſciples to ſee, as in admiration of her bounty: and <hi>David</hi> here upon <hi>Nathans</hi> rebuke, a contrite ſinner preſents the Lord with his offering, even ſuch he had, <hi>a broken heart;</hi> and goeth away well perſwaded or ſatisfied concerning Gods acceptance, <hi>O God thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may ſee there is a double uſe of that I am to ſay: Firſt, Preparatory, like the Lords Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea,</hi> that the luke-warme indifferent Chriſtian, who ſayes he is rich, and needs nothing, may ſee he is poore indeed, and ſo become poore in ſpirit. Secondly, Principall, like the other Epiſtle of comfort to the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> a Church of a broken heart we ſee, and much humbled, but very rich, therefore according to the grace of Gods acceptation.</p>
            <p>Now two things were of great regard in the legall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices or oblations, the ſubject, and the manner; a lambe, or a dove: there is the thing, and both without blemiſh; not the refuſe, not the reverſion, there is the quality. The bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the word of the Lord came downe againſt <hi>Iudah,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the table was come into contempt; and if you offer the blinde, ſaith he, for ſacrifice, is it not evill? and if you offer the lame and ſicke, is it not evill? carry theſe to your Prince, and can he be pleaſed with you, and can he accept your perſons ſaith the Lord of hoſts, <hi>Malac.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>The greateſt man alive, let him come to the Table of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6574:15"/> Lord to receive of his viſible and inviſible word, with an unwaſht, irreverent, and dead heart, and the very Sacrament and word he taketh are his judgements for not diſcerning, and becauſe of his contempt; wherefore King <hi>David</hi> offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth like himſelfe, that is, according to Gods owne heart: Firſt, for the materialls, <hi>his heart:</hi> Secondly, for the forme and qualification, <hi>his heart broken and contrite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That very <hi>Caruncula,</hi> that little fleſh, or part of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the heart, ſome from the triangular figure of that obſerve a ſeat, and receptacle not of the round world, but of the bleſſed Trinity, yea, and ſome gather this ſame doctrine from the letters of the word <hi>Cor.</hi> But the heart, it meaneth more ſpiritually, and firſt, the underſtanding, in which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Cor excaecatum,</hi> a blinded heart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. And <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſayes, <hi>The foole hath ſaid in his heart; in corde ſuo</hi> that is, in his unhallowed, unbroken underſtanding. Secondly, the heart is the conſcience, ſo <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſmote him. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is the deſiring part of the ſoule, <hi>Quid eſt cor tuum, niſi voluntas tua,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard;</hi> Love the Lord with all thy heart; and out of the abundance of the heart, &amp;c. <hi>Vbi theſaurus, ibi cor,</hi> our affections, our wills live with our trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, <hi>Vbi ancant, non ubi animant.</hi> Fourthly, the heart is the complete ſoule quite through; With the heart we beleeve, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. with the act of the underſtanding, conceiving; and with the armes of the will and affiance; conſenting. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. God which ſearcheth the heart, that is, the thoughts, the conſcience, the affections, the whole depth of the ſoule, a thing, which neither the ſight of man can reach, nor the law of man can cenſure.</p>
            <p>This is the ſubject of <hi>Davids</hi> ſacrifice, the matter, but without forme, and void as it was in the beginning; the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or information, the due trimming to the Lords Altar, followes in theſe words, <hi>[Broken and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rite]</hi> and to take them and apply them to the ſubject in order. Firſt, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, yea, <hi>Nathan</hi> uſes this method with <hi>David,</hi> by the parable of the Ewe lambe, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. Firſt of all he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces the judgement, breaketh that, maketh <hi>David</hi> plyable to underſtand himſelfe, for the judgement unbroken ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6574:16"/> of ſinne, thus <hi>David</hi> makes no matter of numbring the people, ſo did pride hood-winke reaſon; upon his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion he confeſſes he did very fooliſhly, or without any true underſtanding. S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo underſtood, as if he did well to perſecute the ſaith of Chriſt, but upon his repentance his judgement altered, I did it ignorantly, ſaith he, and I am the leaſt of the Apoſtles, not worthy to be ſo called, yea, an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ortive, or one borne out of time, becauſe I did perſecute the Church of God. Surely, the reaſon why wee ſo rarely repent in truth is, becauſe we allow ſinne in our judgement, our minde diſlikes it not, and we have no apprehenſion of the danger of it, that it is ſo deadly, and therefore we refuſe the Phyſicke of contrition, becauſe we conceive that, as a thing more than needs: we conſider not, that God is as well juſt as mercifull, and cannot poſſibly be ſerved without repentance, and therefore this holy informing, it deales firſt at the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; as in the caſe of comfort, namely, againſt the feares of death, faith cheeres up the heart by meditation, or min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it of the bleſſed promiſes, that the judgement rectified, and made to underſtand death inwardly, as it is without the <hi>larvae,</hi> the ſhapes it appeareth in to ignorants and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, we may be ſo reſolved, and ſetled, and not to be ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed for death; even ſo in the caſe of renovation, the Lord alters and breaks the imaginations of the heart, firſt of all layeth open to our eye the heinouſneſſe of our ſinfull eſtate in generall, and then commeth home to us, that we relent in particular.</p>
            <p>Yea, contrition giveth the minde, the underſtanding a right reflection, that it ſees it ſelfe rightly without the vaile, and ſcales of ſuperficiall proud blinde Science. The contrite heart feeleth how heavy the wings of depraved reaſon are, and how it hovers like <hi>Noahs</hi> Raven, <hi>Super profundum, ſine fundo;</hi> and like the earth receives the light onely <hi>in ſuperficie,</hi> in the ſurface of it, and in things divine, how it builds rather upon negation to know what the truth is not, than what it is; how uncapable, yea, averſe it is ſince the fall from the right ſcanning of truth, that the very Philoſophers, the beſt or wiſeſt heathen, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6574:16"/> 
               <hi>They became vaine in their imaginations of God, Rom.</hi> 1. and indeed the naturall man judgeth of divine truths but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his owne ſenſes, receives no more in religion than he can ſhew reaſon for, not reaſon of the word or divine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but reaſon of nature, or demonſtration: So the things of God which are ſpiritually diſcerned, or with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite eye, carry a kinde of contrariety to him, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted knowledge or perſwaſion of Gods goſpell, is not to be had in the worldly wiſe, who doe not, who will not ſo farre renounce their conceited knowledge, and ſubdue their imaginations, as farre as they exalt themſelves againſt the word, or have repugnance to Gods knowledge.</p>
            <p>Now in the works of repentance or contrition, when the Lord puts a holy light into the heart, this eye of the ſoule, he makes it ſimple and ſubmiſſe, <hi>The Law of the Lord is pure, making wiſe the ſimple, Pſal.</hi> 19. So that reaſon it comes to conclude with <hi>Iewell,</hi> the peereleſſe Biſhop, <hi>Gratias ago Deo, quod ignorantiam meam non ignoro,</hi> God I thanke thee, that I am not ignorant of my ignorance.</p>
            <p>But faith, when it winnes upon us firſt, it finds reaſon ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting like <hi>Iezabel</hi> painting her face, dreſſing her head, and looking out at the window, till contrition, which like the Baptiſt, uſhers the way of the Lord, calleth to our thoughts, and ſayes with <hi>Iehu,</hi> throw her downe, and if they yeeld not, but advance themſelves againſt God too, it ſayes of them alſo, as <hi>Edom</hi> ſaid of Iſrael, Downe with them, downe with them, even to the ground.</p>
            <p>Contrition, it breaketh the underſtanding, maketh it teachable, and glad of Gods wayes; as they that were ſtung with the fiery ſerpents, were glad to looke to the brazen ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; ſo the broken ſoule with earneſt expectation, <hi>erecto ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite,</hi> waiteth for the manifeſtation of Chriſt and his grace; <hi>Omne humidum facilè alieno termino.</hi> But take a man, when the ſunne of much proſperity, and the like temptations, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hale, and draw out this holy moiſture of contrition, and the Lord of life, the Sonne of God, though he then approve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ne're ſo much before him by word, and works, yet like the Scribes and Phariſees, ſeeing, hee will not perceive, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6574:17"/> learning, he will not underſtand; let the Lord ſing of mercy, and he needs it not, or of judgement, and he feareth it not: I referre you to Saint <hi>Auſten,</hi> the third booke of his <hi>Confeſſ.</hi> the fifth chapter, yea, let common experience ſpeake, if ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny an impenitent heart preacheth not, talketh not, diſputeth not ſubtilly of the doctrines of God, and hath no right knowledge of them, nor acknowledging, but is even made up, and mixt, of doubtings, unbeleefe, and errour? and <hi>Where is the diſputer of this world,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Contrariwiſe, as <hi>Abraham</hi> went to offer his onely ſonne upon the mount of <hi>Moriah,</hi> and never once adviſed with na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon, he left his ſervants at the foot of the hill, leſt by their clamours and diſſwaſions he might be diſturbed in his ſacrifice; ſo the contrite broken heart, the mind thus quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of God, obeyeth the call of God, ſubdueth it ſelfe, and becommeth a ſlave to his word; <hi>Da quod jubes, &amp; jube quod vis,</hi> Gods commands are not grievous to him, but he is ready whereſoever he ſees, thus ſaith the Lord, to intruſt himſelfe to the word. Say unto his ſoule, that man was by the breath of the Lord, and the world was by his word at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, he ſtands not with <hi>Galen,</hi> to cenſure <hi>Moſes</hi> for want of demonſtration: ſay unto him, that God Almighty was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate, and the mother a Virgin delivered of her Maker; he learnes not to diſpute where the Cherubins are ſaid to vaile, but ſaith with the Centurion, <hi>Domine dic verbum, &amp; ſana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur ſervus tuus,</hi> the contrite underſtanding taketh the Lord at his word, though hee ſeeth not his owne reaſon for it, he followes the word of God in all formes, <hi>Vt aqua ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſulcantem digitum.</hi> And as one ſaid, having read the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> the things I know, and the things I know not, <hi>omnia fortia, &amp; generoſa;</hi> ſo he of Gods Scriptures, they be celeſtiall, and good all; and what he cannot fadome, he adoreth, and ſaith, O the depths of Gods counſells! in ſumme, he hath all divinity <hi>in praeparatione animi,</hi> in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſubmit to the word, as it ſhall bee revealed to him, and ever ſaith, Now faith ariſe, and ſleeping hope awake, awake my glory, and though reaſon would comprehend no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, beleeveth all. <hi>Agrippina</hi> the mother of <hi>Nero</hi> ſaid,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6574:17"/> 
               <hi>o ccidar modo imperet;</hi> but the faith of the contrite minde ſaith, <hi>imperabo modò occidat,</hi> I will truſt the Lord, though he kill me: with <hi>Abraham,</hi> againſt hope, hee beleeves in hope, and offers himſelfe in ſacrifice to the Lord by an holy vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence upon his carnall reaſonings: he ſeeketh to bring every thought in captivity to the obedience of Chriſt, and he rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koneth of all ſcience, how ſubtil ſoever, but as droſſe, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the excellencie of the knowledge of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour: yea, that ſweet and pretious name, (with <hi>Ignatius</hi> the martyr) he hath ſuch a dear impreſſion of it, that it ſeemeth riveted, and graven, <hi>In tabulis cordis,</hi> in the tables of his heart or underſtanding, for now hee ſees well, and ſayes with <hi>Themiſtocles, periiſſem niſi periiſſem,</hi> I had utterly periſhed, if with the prodigall, by remorſe and contrition, I had not beene rein'd in to ſee my foule miſtakings, and ſo to ſeeke and returne to God my mercifull father in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, this contrite underſtanding is the onely <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus,</hi> he delights in peace, and therefore goeth on warily, and timorouſly, and feareth to frame out articles of faith, from the mould of his reaſon, much leſſe to frame out oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions againſt manifeſt truths of Scripture, or to thruſt out publike poſitions, from any private diſpoſitions, <hi>ludere cum Deo;</hi> yea hee dares not let himſelfe bee deceived with any hate, or evill opinion of good, whereſoever it is profeſſed, leſt he commeth in the end to deceive himſelfe with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light or good opinion of evill. In ſumme, he minds, and is taken up moſt of all, how, or by what meanes he may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the devill, rather than how to confute his gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers, and bewaile the time, that ever the ſimplicity of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, ſhould loſe it ſelfe in the Labyrinths of beleefe, and that the word ſhould be <hi>tam ferax religionum,</hi> ſo fruitfull of opinions, and ſo barren of piety, as <hi>Lipſius</hi> once ſpake; and this is to be transformed by the renewing of the minde, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, this is contrition, <hi>in ſpiritu mentis,</hi> in the ſpirit of our minde, in the underſtanding.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſeat of contrition, is the Conſcience: the nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming away of the skirts of <hi>Sauls</hi> garment, and a raſh wiſh
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6574:18"/> for the waters of <hi>Bethlem;</hi> if theſe ſmote <hi>David</hi> to the heart, his conſcience, if it was of ſo tender a touch, ſurely his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous fact in numbring the people, and this <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially this ſcarlet, or double-dyed ſinne, of which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Nathan</hi> rebukt him, the conſcience of this heinous ſinne melts him away like water, as wee ſee in this Pſalme: a Pſalme we may all take up, as <hi>Gregorie Nazianzene</hi> did the Lamentations of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> to make us weepe for our ſins and tranſgreſſions.</p>
            <p>But conſcience is a part of the practicke underſtanding, as Gods Deputy ſitting within to judge, to ſee, and cenſure us together with God: it is a certaine ſecret feeling, or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our deeds, which leaveth behinde it, or imprints the motions of joy, or ſorrow, hope or feare, confidence or ſhame; it is an inward key, which unlocketh and openeth the doores and barres of our hearts, that the grieved ſpirit commeth forth, like good <hi>Lot</hi> out of the houſe of ſinne, and ſayes to the man of <hi>Sodome, O deale not ſo wickedly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as the great Turke permits every one to live in his owne religion, ſo they pay him in his tribute; ſo the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hardned or ſeared, permits the appetites to their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſo it may partake; it neglects the ſoule, to pleaſe the ſenſe; it prevaricates, and willfully ſuppreſſes the true ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict or teſtimonie, and is idle, and doth not its office, but luls us aſleepe in our ſinne, and layes the raines on the necks of our wilde and untamed luſts. <hi>Cor dilatatum,</hi> a ſpacious looſe heart, a Chiverell conſcience; and indeed, when the minde is in meere darkneſſe, as in the ſtate of unregenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or when it is overflowed or dimmed with the dampe of ſome temptation, or waſting ſinne, as it may befall the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, no marvell then if this particular knowledge bee darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe too, and our inward thoughts ceaſe from their accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing for a ſeaſon; for the ſoule, it hath not now an actuall or exerciſed ſenſe and light, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, to diſcerne the proportions of good and evill; being poſſeſſed with a ſpirit of ſlumber in any meaſure, ſo farre it is no rightfull Judge, no more than the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6574:18"/> blinde man is of colours: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence without ſcience, a heart like <hi>Nabals,</hi> benum'd and ſenſleſſe.</p>
            <p>And the manner or growth of it is thus; Originall ſinne ſends out actuall, and they leave a ſtraine, a diſpoſition to ſinne ſo againe, and ſinning ſo againe, ſlight impreſſions of evill become radicate, and habituall, till the <hi>callum,</hi> the cruſt, deadneſſe or ſecurity in ſinne comes over the ſoule; the buds of infirmity ſteale to the twigs of negligence, and they to the tyranny of cuſtome, and then audacious and grand ſinnes plead preſcription, and like a ſtout tenant take no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and this is <hi>nervus ferreus,</hi> the iron ſinew, the heart of adamant. When Camels, groſſe ſinnes paſſe, and digeſt without remorſe, and this our Church in her Letany depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates moſt Chriſtianly, <hi>From hardneſſe of heart, and contempt of thy word and commandements, good Lord deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the contrite conſcience is the very contrary, and that it may have its beginning thus; as <hi>Ioab</hi> would not be moved to come to <hi>Abſalom</hi> till his fields were ſet on fire; ſo we oft-times, we have no heart, no perceiving of our eſtate towards God, till affliction, like fire ceaſeth upon us, till with <hi>Manaſſes</hi> our chaine, or with <hi>Hezekiah</hi> our bed of ſickneſſe, or with <hi>Mauritius</hi> death of wife and children rouze and ſtartle us, and wring forth a holy confeſſion, <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus eſt Deus, &amp; juſta ſunt judicia ejus.</hi> For thus the good Shepherd oft-times ſends after his ſheepe, poverty, perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſickneſſe, and the like, to hurry them backe when they goe aſtray from him; and the heart, indeed the conſcience, is in a very ill caſe, which ffliction cannot mollifie, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.8. the ſonnes of God learne obedience by the things they ſuffer, and for this wee may learne to take well the Lords caſtigations, kiſſe the rod as often as it betides us.</p>
            <p>Againe, we muſt not thinke much to wait at the poſts of Gods houſe continually, to liſten, as <hi>David</hi> did, to his word in the mouth of <hi>Nathan,</hi> his word in the miniſtery of it, God uſeth to bleſſe it, and to put forth his ſpirit with it, that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6574:19"/> with <hi>David,</hi> our heart ſmiteth us, we tremble with <hi>Foelix,</hi> we melt with <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> we are pierced to the quicke, like thoſe thouſands at S. <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon; and we are rifled, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced in our conſciences, like thoſe in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Law ſin is dead, Rom.</hi> 7. It is not acknowledged; the word is <hi>Gladius Domini,</hi> the ſword of the Lord, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. It opens our ſinnes to our eyes, and <hi>Malleus Domini,</hi> the Lords hammer to breake our ſtony heart, <hi>Ierem.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> being called by the Lord in the wilderneſſe before the burning mount, he commanded them his word, and Law not to be ſuppreſt in ſecrecie, but to be pitched up in the eye of all the world, even that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous heart might looke on it, as Chriſt did on Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, with weeping eyes, to ſee how ſhort he comes of that hee ſhould, and that the diſſembling heart might have his paintings and colours, his faces of ſanctitie, thawed all by the fire of Gods juſtice: The Word of the Lord is ſpirit and life, a ſacred perſpective it is, wee may behold in it our ſins of thought, deſire, and deed, and thereupon ſee how the hoſt of heaven, with chariots of fire, march in array, ready preſt to charge; the curſe of God, how ready it is to light on us. A ſight for which <hi>Davids</hi> heart becommeth ſo intenerate, that hee a King, commits a Pſalme to bee ſung here in the Church, wherein his owne capitall ſins ſhould be blazed to all poſteritie by his owne confeſſion, a ſight for which S. <hi>Auſten</hi> needs would, that this verie Pſalme ſhould bee ſet over his bed night and day, that with teares hee might read over his tranſgreſſions, a roll wherof he hath left in his owne Confeſſions, which is admirable to the Reader.</p>
            <p>And Conſcience indeed is a ſleeping Lion, it will awaken, in the evill houre we ſhall finde it, our owne heart then ſeeks occaſions againſt us, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeakes; and let not him thinke, who hath not yet the ſting of his ſinne, that he hath not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended; it watches the conſcience, till the time of moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; but the Lord, by this conſcience of ſinne, awakens thoſe to life, that are his; by this ſenſibleneſſe, or accuſing of the heart, he doth much in our calling to grace, and in our
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6574:19"/> continuing in it; for the contrite, or wounded conſcience, dealeth not with our evill motions, as <hi>Darius</hi> did with <hi>Alexander,</hi> ſuffer them to paſſe, or come over the heart, as he did the Helleſpont, till they beare all before them; but like <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that killed the infants of Iſrael, leſt they ſhould overgrow his Countrey: So the truly broken, and tender heart growes daily verie conſcientious of everie the leaſt ſin, and taketh care therefore of the ſerpents in the ſhell, <hi>Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere parvulos ad petram,</hi> to cruſh the verie occaſions of ſin, and with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> it ſhaketh of the vipers from the fingers ends, at the firſt motion of evill, leſt ſuggeſtion beget de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and that multiply from action into cuſtome, like the fiſh that ſwim downe the ſtreames of Jordan, <hi>in mare mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum,</hi> into the dead ſea.</p>
            <p>Yea, and in the midſt of all our proſperities &amp; pleaſures, it is the qualitie of a contrite conſcience, ever and anon to ſend us downe an holy feare, as it were a bucket into the bottome of our hearts, to taſte the waters, whether or no they bee ſtill, ſweet, and cleere, and ſo to preſerve us from relapſing, or reciduation; I will put my feare into their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>The third thing which partakes this contrition or brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, is the will and affections; <hi>O Lord, create in me a cleane heart,</hi> verſ. 10. which is as if hee had ſaid; O Lord, inable me to breake my will and affections from frowardneſſe and perverſeneſſe againſt thy will, to which I am bound by the cords of thy word: will and affections, theſe are the horſe and mule, that muſt bee hold in, or broken by the bit and bridle, as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaketh, yea, the horſe may caſt his rider, and himſelfe ſtand upright ſtill; but affections indanger not the ſoule, but by ruining themſelves, as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> horſe, and the riders alſo were drowned in the red ſea: affections, theſe are the inteſtine foes, the Jebuſites which fight ſtill within our borders, yea, which ruſh in upon us oft times amidſt our beſt devotions. S. <hi>Hierom</hi> in the wilderneſſe, among all his mortifications, had enough to doe to breake them; and S. <hi>Baſil</hi> complaines, that when hee had forſaken the ſocietie of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6574:20"/> men, he could not forſake his owne affections, his owne heart haunted him, and purſued him ſtill: But <hi>Iſmael</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Agar</hi> the bond-woman, when he would be oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſonne of the free, he was thruſt out of <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe: The Father of the faithfull gives us even in this a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, namely, that we breake with thoſe affections, which hinder our holy purpoſes, that wee baniſh them, and binde them to their obedience and good behaviour; and this it is to ſacrifice our affections, or to ſeparate them to the Lord, when wee ſet them apart from their old exceſſes, and this is <hi>Sacrificium vivum,</hi> as the Apoſtle cals it, the living ſacrifice of a broken heart or affection, a ſacrifice that liveth the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter after it is offered.</p>
            <p>Beloved, as in a common fire, when the flames take hold of our houſes, we inſtantly run to the rivers, to the water, to quench it: ſo our hearts within, our affections naturally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet on fire with hell, as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh, what ſhould we doe, but flye to the river of contrition and repentance? This Red ſea of remorſefull ſorrow, our ſpirituall <hi>Pharaoh</hi> drownes in it, with all his armies of vicious luſts, here they periſh together: And as in a common ſiege, when the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies reares up workes or edifices to the wals of a Citie, and from thence ſhoots, and hurles fire into it, a chiefe remedy is to dig ſecret wayes and paſſages for water under the earth unto thoſe fabricks, that ſo their foundation may weaken, &amp; fall; ſo a tower of Babel, of inordinate affections, being ſet up againſt our ſoule, and therein the Archers of Satan, Pride, Luſt, Avarice, and the like, ſhooting the fire of ſin into our hearts, let us with the <hi>Magdalene</hi> derive thither even tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the ſecret veines of our hearts, flouds of contrition and repentance, for this ſhakes the verie ground-worke of Satans holds: the gates of the rivers ſhall be opened, and the palace ſhall be diſſolved; that I may ſpeake in the words of the Prophet <hi>Nahum</hi> 2.6. <hi>O poenitentiae lachryma rutulantior au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, ſplendidior Sole,</hi> ſaith <hi>Anſelme,</hi> O Contrition, more ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diant than gold, more ſhining than the Sun, <hi>reſpicis avariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, horres luxuriam,</hi> and ſo forth; thou hateſt covetouſneſſe,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6574:20"/> thou abhorreſt luxurie, thou breakeſt the power and yoke of evill affections: Thou art the axe laid to the root of the heart, thou art the <hi>Catholicon,</hi> the univerſall medicine, that workes upon everie peccant humour, thou makeſt us ready to part with all bad deſires in obedience to the Lords com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: for this godly contrition is a diſtaſte of ſin as ſin, and ſo it is impartiall againſt whatſoever comes, as a tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt God. <hi>I have refrained my feet from everie evill way, that I may keepe thy word, Pſal.</hi> 119.101. Worldly ſorrow hideth our ill affections, reſtraineth open breakings out, and that's all: Like the cold aire, it doth but drive the diſeaſe of ſin inward, <hi>Abſcondit vitia, non abſcindit;</hi> But godly ſorrow, or contrition enters and ſearches, it cancels and ſacrifices the evill that is in our moſt covert, and retired inclining, and withall it cals out repentance, it is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſigh in ſecret, it cals the heart, the affection into the eye, to weepe for ſinne with S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and into the mouth to confeſſe it with King <hi>David,</hi> yea, and into the hands to break it off by good workes, the offices of pietie and pitie: <hi>Poros aperit cordis,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Gregorie:</hi> And the contrite affection is of all the openeſt, the eaſieſt to commiſerate, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo well it is acquainted with its owne evill, that who is ill affected with ſinne and miſerie, that melts not? And ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective is it to Gods ire and diſpleaſure, which it hath weighed and taſted, that the leaſt ſymptome, or ſigne of it, upon it ſelfe or others, diſſolves it into feare and trembling, and this is the circumciſion of the heart, the breaking or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition of the will and affections.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, to ſumme up all together, the heart meaneth no leſſe here, than the ſoule complete, or quite thorow, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triti cordis holocauſtum,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Cyprian: The perfect heart, Pſal.</hi> 101. Not perfection in everie part, but perfection of all the parts, <hi>Integritas animi. Create in me a cleane heart,</hi> ſaith <hi>David:</hi> before, as in the firſt creation, God made man per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in all members and parts: ſo in the ſecond, in regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is a new birth, or breaking of all the powers of the ſoule in ſome good meaſure, and ſay not thou art contrite, or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6574:21"/> renued in the eye of the ſoule, in thy underſtanding and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, unleſſe it goe alſo to thy bowels, to thy will and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; the good heart is a broken, but not a divided heart; <hi>their heart is divided, now ſhall they be found faulty, Hoſ.</hi> 10.2. the Lord liketh not to have his right parted with the naturall mother, he will part with his right rather; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt become a captive, and conſcience an accuſer; will and affections flexible, and laid downe at the feet of the Lord; the heart contrite, is the ſoule affected throughly, the word ſignifieth a grinding to powder, as of the corne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the milſtones.</p>
            <p>And great reaſon and ground is there for this; the Lord beſides his law delivered on the mount, made us in <hi>Eden</hi> a new and everlaſting covenant, even that his holy ſonne, the eſſentiall image of his perſon, ſhould come in our nature, by the price of redemption paid in his bloud, to reconcile us to God; ſo did the mighty God make a holy and ſpeciall league with his mortall foe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith the Apoſtle, meerely for the good pleaſure of his grace, and bound himſelfe by as free promiſe, to make the faithfull, his Church, a joynture of all the joyes of heaven; yet we rebell againſt the moſt high, and lightly regard his counſels; if we looke up to heaven, we ſee the ſeat indeed of a tender Father, but infinitely have we ſinned againſt him and it; if wee gaſpe in our trouble for the comfort of Chriſt his merits, the Redeemer of the world, wee ſee how vilely our owne evill words and deeds crucifie him daily, and put him to open ſhame, grieving his ſpirit, quenching his gifts and abuſing his very grace.</p>
            <p>Now the Adamant ſoftens when warme bloud is ſhed on it; and the bloud of the Lord Jeſus ſo graciouſly effuſed on us, and for us, the riches of this goodneſſe ſhould lead us to remorſe, and to repent of our ſinnes, even in love of the Lord for his mercies, yea, no ſlight affection, no curſory Lord have mercie upon us, ſhould ſuffice us; with <hi>Ieremy</hi> we ſhould call for a cottage in the wilderneſſe, and then broken to water, waſh with teares the day wherein wee were borne.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6574:21"/> And, O that the precious balmes, the mercies of our Lord Jeſus, the ſenſe of what he hath done and ſuffered for us, ſhould not mollifie us, and make us relent; yea, let us bee ſicke with his love, the loves of Chriſt conſtraine, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. And if before time we have ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and loved the Lord, even for feare of wrath; henceforth let us feare God for love, and repent, and ſorrow for our ſinnes in love, and ſo our contrition will become entire, and of the whole heart, becauſe the love of God is abſolute, and infinite.</p>
            <p>Now there bee who make a trade, yea, a ſport and a merriment of their ſinnes, who can count, and chronicle their diſſoluteneſſe with delight, ſo farre they be from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition and remorſe, and they no doubt will laugh in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leeves to heare of this bruiſing and maceration of ſpirit; and let the deceived world take theſe for godly people, jolly fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, they ſhall die like men, like the beaſts that periſh: the Lord gave ſtrength to the horſe, and clothed his necke with thunder, ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> he mockes at feare, and beleeves not the ſound of the trumpet, yet if the quiver of the Lord rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle againſt him, he is afraid as a graſhopper. Obdurate god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſpirits, whoſe hearts like <hi>Prometheus,</hi> grow fat and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid in the night of their ignorance, there is a day when the Vulture of feare, and heavineſſe of heart ſhall ſeaze and gnaw upon them, death ſhall feed upon the ungodly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. and when they come indeed in ſight of death, and the fatall anchor beginnes to fall, that can never be weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againe, and the luſty ſaylers, the ſenſes, that rowed them over the ſtreames of carnall pleaſures, ſtand amazed, and faile, and the waves of horror ſwell and breake upon the crackt veſſell, and the unwiſe Pilot reaſon as at the end of his wits, cryeth out with him in <hi>Seneca, Huc ego quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum vens,</hi> Lord how may this be? yea, their owne heart and conſcience then amidſt their other evills, ſhall returne upon them like the Raven, in blacke and ſable weeds, with the law, the curſe, and all the aberrations of life in his mouth, and what tongue can tell their ſorrow? Like as the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6574:22"/> chaſed Deere, recovering about the end of the day ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle breathing, ſtands and liſtens unto the cries of them that ſeeke his bloud, and ſeeing the way ſtopt, pants, and ſhuts his fearef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll eyes, and finding his legs faile him at laſt, lies downe, deſpaires, and dies; ſo they oft-times, and amidſt their agonie, faine would give a thouſand Rammes, and a thouſand Rivers of oyle, and the fruit of their body, the choiceſt goods they have, to be aſſoyled from the ſinne of their ſoule. O conſider we this, that we doe not quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God; without contrition and repentance the Lord wee ſee is a conſuming fire, and the impenitent ſooner or later, have there no peace, their hell, even upon earth: and if ſo, in the firſt day, at the day of death at leaſt, what ſhall we ſay to the day of revelation, the day of the generall judgement. Surely Kings ſhall repine then at the beggers joy, and mighty Emperours ſhall ſay with <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> how much better is it to have beene the true member of Chriſt his Church, than the head of an Empire? For the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſhall bee ſeene then to gather up the ſcattered peeces of every contrite and broken heart, and to draw out to their encouragement the teares of repentance, which the Lord had treaſured, or put up into his bottle, and to take quite from them the cup of trembling, and to reach it forth into the hands of all impenitents, and remorſeleſſe ſinners; and ſo I have done with the ſacrifice, <hi>The broken and contrite hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> and proceed to the ſecond branch of the text, the Lords gentle acceptance, <hi>O God thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If in the conſcience of ſin, the broken heart tremble to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before the Lord, and though humbled, yet feareth leſt God ſhould not accept of him, behold his Cordiall, God will not deſpiſe him: Not deſpiſe him? Yea, deare ſhall he be in Gods ſight, that the Sunne may not burne him by day, nor the Moone by n ght: For as in the Scripture there is an exceſſe of ſpeech, when more is ſpoken than is underſtood, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as caſt out the beame that is in thine owne eye: So there is alſo a defect of ſpeech, when more is underſtood than ſpoken, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as deſpiſe not prophecie, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6574:22"/> meaneth we ſhould honour that gift of the Holy Ghoſt much: So here the words muſt be underſtood above the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and meane much more than is ſpoken, namely, that God will highly eſteeme, and comfort, and revive the ſpirit of the humble; for Chriſt his ſweet allures and invitations of the laden and contrite heart to come to him, ſhew that it is no deſpicable matter: a thing to be deſpiſed is fruitleſſe, and of ſmall uſe, but this oblation of <hi>David</hi> is of exceeding much validitie, and therefore he cals it firſt, A ſacrifice; an offering it is, wherewith if we approach before the Lord, we have a good evidence before us, the pledge of our peace, and remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins, becauſe God hath ſo promiſed to accept of us for Chriſt his ſake. Secondly, <hi>David</hi> cals it <hi>Sacrificia,</hi> in the plurall number, Sacrifices, becauſe a penitent heart, why this is one for all, it includes and ſummes up all that whatſoever it is that God accepts, it is in ſtead of all, no ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle ſacrifice. Thirdly, the Prophet cals it <hi>Sacrificia Dei,</hi> the ſacrifices of the Lord, of the Lord by way of Emphaſis, or excellence, as Nineveh, the Citie of God, or the exceeding great Citie, <hi>Ionah</hi> 3. and the trees of God are goodly Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80. and <hi>Opera Dei,</hi> the works of God, or which God approves, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. So the contri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e heart is the ſacrifices of God, ſuch as to God is verie pleaſing, an heart that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents and beleeves in Chriſts bloud, and ſeekes mercie for the ſame; yea, though it have ſinned much, is yet ſuch a worke of God, wherein God cannot but bee well pleaſed. From the heart are the iſſues of life and death, it rowles the lower ſpheres with it; and therefore though <hi>Davids</hi> eyes were adulterous, his hands imbrued, and his verie lips ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up with his ſinnes, as we ſee at the fifteenth verſe. Yet no ſooner doth the Lord open his mouth, but his prayer is for his heart and ſpirit; for till God give us grace to draine that fen, or ſinke of evill, which is in our heart, in vaine ſhould we labour about our words, or deeds. And therefore <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodorus</hi> in <hi>Plutarch</hi> dreamed, that his body being cut in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and caſt into a ſeething cauldron, his heart leapt up and ſaid, <hi>Ego horum tibi cauſa fui,</hi> I was the cauſe of all this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6574:23"/> And therefore the Phariſies, thoſe old hypocrites, when they cleanſed but the outſide, Chriſt &amp; the ſecond <hi>Elias</hi> called them vipers, and a generation of vipers, and bid them <hi>Mundare priùs quod intùs,</hi> cleanſe within firſt, or be ſincere at heart, and humble that; for till contrition come to the heart, their religion like a mill, it moved not without the wind of vaine glorie; and the light of their good works, the lampe of their charitie did not ſhine, and burne without the oyle of mans praiſe, they had no zeale but in publike, and in the corners of the ſtreet: whereas, the heart once well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and humbled, then would they enter their cloſets to pray, and ſeeke in their devotions not their owne, but Gods glorie, and though man would ſuper-admire, or deifie them for any their good deeds, yet the heart well toucht with a ſenſe of its owne infirmitie, it would retaine its humilitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt the holieſt and beſt performances, it would give backe to God his due. Of ſuch behoofe is the broken heart, the iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of it is ſinceritie, and that is the ſoule of all vertue; and therefore the contrite heart is, as wee ſee, the verie center wherein the lines of Gods graces meet, and to which they run, and ſo it hath Gods ſpeciall love and acceptation for its circumference.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[O God thou wilt not deſpiſe.]</hi> The ſummons of death went out againſt <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> hee retires like the Sunne in his diall, he goeth backe to the Lord, hee mournes in his prayer like a Dove, he chatters like a Crane or Swallow, and <hi>I have heard thy prayers, I have ſeene thy teares, behold,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will adde unto thy dayes fifteene yeares, Iſa.</hi> 38. The ſummons of death, the threats of Gods Law and Word, were read in the cares of <hi>Ioſiah</hi> the King, and his heart was tender, hee humbled himſelfe before the Lord, hee rent his clothes, hee wept ſore, and the Lord ſent <hi>Huldah</hi> the Propheteſſe, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure him that his contrition was not deſpiſed, and he ſhould bee gathered to his fathers in peace, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 22.19. The ſummons of death were out againſt Nineveh that great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſhee relents, ſhee fits her downe in ſack-cloth, and turnes her ſilkes into aſhes, Peeres and people, none excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6574:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> come downe, <hi>è ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lio in ſolum:</hi> and by and by the hand of vengeance, that was waved over them, is taken aſide, and the writ of bloud is reverſed. <hi>Surge deſperatio, vade ad Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niven:</hi> Now riſe deſpaire, and goe to Nineveh: Thinke how Nineveh was not refuſed, though the cry of her ſins went up to Heaven before the cry of her teares: And who art thou then that ſayeſt with <hi>Spira,</hi> I cannot be ſaved; or with <hi>Cain, Major iniquitas, Mine iniquitie is greater than God can forgiue? Mentiris, Cain; Cain,</hi> thou lyeſt, ſaith <hi>Auſten,</hi> thy ſinnes bee they in number as the haires of thine head, Gods mercies are as the ſtarres of Heaven, above all his workes: Can we with <hi>Elias</hi> ſurround our ſacrifice with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, our prayers and devotions with holy ſorrow, for the wants and defects of our devotions; yea, if but with ſorrow for not ſorrowing ſo heartily, ſo earneſtly as we ought, the Lord will not deſpiſe us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In ipſius praeſentia nunquam ſupervacuae mendicant lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae veniam,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> Never did teares or true contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion beg before the Lord in vaine: <hi>Nec unquam patitur re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſam contriti cordis holocauſtum,</hi> And never did the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the broken heart finde repulſe at the hands of God: The Iſrael of God that ever is fighting with <hi>Ammon,</hi> and conflicting to the verie Sun-ſetting, and the man of God that ſtill holds up his hands and prayes, life and victorie is layd up for them in the boſome of Jeſus Chriſt our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. And now let him be hid to the world, and deſpiſed, that the verie abjects have him in deriſion, his light ſhall breake forth like the Sun, through the continuall interceſſion of Chriſt for him, and all the world ſhall ſee, that God will not deſpiſe him.</p>
            <p>We ſee Gods manner or method, <hi>Deducit ad inferos &amp; reducit,</hi> When he brings a ſinner to him, hee leadeth him as he did the Iſraelites, thorow a perillous wilderneſſe into Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, thorow Hell to Heaven, by mount Sinai to mount Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thorow painfull contrition, and ſorrow, and ſenſe of his ſinnes and corruptions, to the conſolations and peace of the Holy Ghoſt, ſo that being well experienced in the miſeries
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6574:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> of his ſinfull eſtate, he ſhall feare to returne into Aegypt, the bitter impreſſion and ſting of his ſins, which ſtill remaineth, it will be a checke to him from looking backe againe: and this may be a reaſon of Gods dealing with us, why hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts the ſacrifice of our hearts contrite and broken.</p>
            <p>But now if we ſhall feare to venture into the wayes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and godlineſſe, for feare of loſing our pleaſures, and being caſt upon the paines of contrition, prayer and wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, we ſee the vanitie of that deluſion, becauſe from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Benonies</hi> ſons of ſorrow, the Lord maketh us to bee <hi>Benjamins</hi> ſons of his owne right hand. From a deluge of contrition to rinſe us, we come to enjoy the certificates of our peace, like his heavenly raine-bow, to ſtrengthen us. In ſenſe of man, <hi>Iobs</hi> contrition was <hi>ignis foeno,</hi> like the fire to the ſtubble, to undoe him, or confound him; but in truth, and in the event it was <hi>ignis auro,</hi> like fire to the gold, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e him and doe him good: For his corruption we ſee aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth incorruption, and this vile bodie riſeth up a glorious bodie, Gods tender mercie a little bounded in for his triall, like a river breaketh forth the more, at the ſluces of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and contrition. <hi>A broken and a contrite heart, ô God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, ſeeing the heart contrite is ſo acceptable an offering to the Lord, let us from the little Spider learne here to begin our amendment, let us begin to mend our web at the middle, our contrition let us ſeek to bring it to the heart. A curſorie confeſſion, a formall faſt, a coat of ſack-cloth, and the like; can theſe quench the flames which ſinne hath blowne and kindled? Leave off renting your garments, ſaith the Prophet, and learne to unharden your hearts, the contrite heart is the oblation that God will not deſpiſe.</p>
            <p>The Romiſh Votarie or Secluſe, how often is her eye caſt downe and heavie, when her heart is an Aetna of vicious affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions? How ſeemes the Jeſuite, as if with S. <hi>Paul</hi> he were crucified to the world, and the world to him, when his ſpirit is with <hi>Lucifer</hi> in the clouds, contriving combuſtions of State? How broken, abject, and vile, ſeeme their begging
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6574:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> Orders, being men of another mould indeed, juſt like the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medians, who play and act the ſiege of Troy, and the teares, of <hi>Priam,</hi> without all ſenſe or touch of that griefe at the heart. True acceptable contrition runs and goes in another ſtraine, by inward ſmart and groanes of heart and ſpirit: it prayes, it vowes, it powres out the ſoule before the Lord, <hi>Lam.</hi> 2. Like the parched earth, it gaſpes towards Heaven, as if it would devoure the clouds, it wreſtleth with the Lord like <hi>Iacob,</hi> with ſtrong ſupplications it repents from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie heart root, and the ſavour of this incenſe aſcends before the throne of the Lord, and returnes not without a bleſſing, yea, not without ſome inward pledge in the iſſue and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Gods mercie and remiſſion: The ſtroke of an wholly accuſing guiltie heart is heavie, <hi>exiccat oſſa, Prov.</hi> 17. but the joy of the contrite repenting heart is incredible, it is <hi>ſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas carnium, Prov.</hi> 14. So ſweet are the iſſues of the contrite heart, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſenſe thereof <hi>Iob</hi> feeleth not the witneſſe of man againſt him, becauſe God would witneſſe for him, <hi>Iob.</hi> 31. and when our hearts dare indeed witneſſe to us, that we are contrite, or doe un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>einedly repent, this makes glad the heart, and is a continuall Jubilee, becauſe it is the co-witneſſe with Gods ſpirit, that we are his, that God hath accepted us.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>A broken and a contrite heart, ô God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg. 10. lin. 4. <hi>for</hi> no, <hi>read</hi> not. pag. ib. lin. 35. <hi>for</hi> nured, <hi>read</hi> inured. p. 11. l 19. <hi>read</hi> cover and hide. p. ib. l. 33. <hi>for</hi> exacts, <hi>read</hi> exact. p. 14. l. 19, 20. <hi>read</hi> in that verie day.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
